hi uh so yeah we travel a lot around the
world every year uh 35 cities last year
and uh we're especially active in uh
South America uh Asia Europe uh Eastern
Europe our our Moscow team is here
welcome to you Anton and elizabeta can
you give them a hand
please and uh part of the German team is
here from Berlin nice to see
[Applause]
[Music]
you and I and some of our sponsors from
Asia are here and thank you for coming
[Applause]
uh
so uh when I teach in Asia you know the
DCI we are teaching things like it's 12
levels some of the levels are about how
to have a successful business how to
start a business uh how to manage a
business and and we also do at one
business conference a lady asked me if
you could apply The Diamond Cutter
principles to her
husband uh fixing her husband's bad
habits and uh so we that created a whole
branch of
DCI uh doing relationships so we help
people all over the world with that
recently uh I just came back from China
we were at the largest mental health
facility in China uh where they treat uh
almost 4,000 uh heroin addicts a year
and we're applying the principles there
uh we're doing a clinical study there on
the effects of meditation and and using
Karma uh to treat drug addiction and so
we have a broad uh range of subjects but
often times when I'm in China uh and
really the audiences in China Taiwan
Singapore Malaysia they are sort of
amazing people and they'll ask me uh
Gesa you know it's very interesting all
of these principles we love applying
them to our normal life but could you
just go deeper you know and we have a
joke when we teach in Asia we say do you
want to go deeper and then people
go and uh so they asked me could you
teach something deeper uh last time I
was there and then sometimes we'll do an
all night teaching uh they'll just say
can we just go to some you know some
small Auditorium and do an all night
teaching on like The Diamond Cutter Su
or something like that so uh when I when
we decided to come to New York uh this
time we had a cancellation in Dubai
uh so we had an extra day in our
schedule the schedule's booked for quite
a many months probably couple years and
so we had an extra day uh so I said well
let's go to New York and let's uh repeat
some of the meditations we did in in
Asia uh for the people who wanted to go
deeper in the Jin kangin The Diamond
Cutter Sutra and so
whoa you didn't turn your phone off uh
so I you know I really enjoy New York I
I I lived and worked here for many years
and I thought you know new a lot of my
older students are here not old in the
sense of age but uh experience so I
thought you would enjoy uh doing these
meditations uh of kamalashila okay
Kamala Sheila lived in around
750 ad uh he was from India and he's
best known for a book called Goro uh
which is called Baka which is the steps
of meditation stages of meditation those
of you who studied meditation through
the three jewels or ACR courses there's
a beautiful poster do you have that one
I don't know you can find it the poster
of the yeah good
luck I told him I'm going to ask for
something he doesn't have but there's a
poster that many of you have studied
meditation from uh at the three jewels
Center and uh it's yeah this is based on
the work of Kamala Sheila okay this
comes from Kamala Sheila and it the
poster was done by my was carved under
the direction of my teacher's
teacher uh so all of that information on
the nine levels of meditation and you
know like a hundred different things to
do during meditation how to watch out
during meditation those are summarized
in this poster from the three volume
work by Kamala Sheila so he's best known
for that uh but he also wrote A
Commentary to The Diamond Cutter Sutra
and that's a very dear Sutra to me there
are only two ancient commentaries one is
by vasu who wrote the Abid mosia and uh
very famous for that all of the Buddhism
in Thailand Sri Lanka Burma is based on
that book uh but the other author of the
commentary was Kamala Sheila and and
there's a commentary to The Diamond
Cutter Sutra in tibetan it's about 130
pages it never reached India because
schwen s came to India just before that
so uh this this teaching didn't reach
China uh and it was never translated
into Chinese the Sanskrit was lost and
uh so we only have the Tibetan text and
you know I like a challenge so I I tried
to crack this text and it took me quite
a while but it's an amazing it's a it's
a beautiful beautiful beautiful text so
I thought I would just
share some of the teachings from that
text in the form of some meditations and
I do these meditations every day uh I
took the first quarter of the text and
cut out 25 different meditations okay
and I'm there summarized in the book you
have the play bill you have
so I'm going to just go through them we
were recently in Taiwan we did this for
like eight hours over two days and we'd
only got halfway through so I don't know
how much a New Yorker can do in an hour
and a half but but we'll try we'll try
to do this my plan is first half I'll do
sort of the meditations which are more
thematic about how to bring meaning to
your life how to improve your life and
then we'll take a break uh for 15
minutes when you hear the bell ring you
come back okay and then we'll just go uh
deeper into the concept of king or
emptiness and how you can apply that to
your life how can you use it to be
successful in your life because The
Diamond Cutter Sutra is perhaps the most
important book about emptiness okay uh
so we'll just
start the name Kamala Sheila I really
like it Kamala means BMA or uh lotus
flower uh like that beautiful pink lotus
flower that that grows in the water and
uh Sheila uh can mean can have two
meanings one is
morality and the other is the way that
you do something it's called nul how you
do something so in this case Kamala
shila's name has two different meanings
one is that a person who leads a a sweet
way of life a person who's helpful to
other PE people good to other people
kind to other people uh they actually in
there's a tradition in India that they
will start to smell like a Lotus okay
their body will start to smell like a
Lotus or or like gardinia or something
so if you have been around these high
llamas who are very you know their life
is very Noble and very proper clean pure
then when you kind of walk by when they
walk by and the what do you call the
wind from their body hits you then you
smell this faint uh lovely fragrance uh
like the faint fragrance of a Lotus so
his name of the author Kamala Sheila
means uh the scent from the kindness of
a high holy person okay like a Lotus
okay so I like that Sheila also means uh
the way of doing something so it can
mean in the Buddhist tradition that uh a
person who who wants to help the world
they want to do something good for the
world then they try to seek out the
worst places uh to go and help people so
you know they avoid the nice places
that's why I don't come to New York so
often
uh you know we go to rough places we've
been to some very rough places uh you
know we've been teaching a lot of people
in in Muslim countries recently in about
10 different countries uh that's why I I
decided not to wear robes I can't show
the videos of this talk in those in some
of those countries so I think it's
important for you know we want the
videos to be available online uh to
different countries where they're not
allow they're not allowed to show videos
of of somebody in robes or something
like that and we go to many very poor
countries and we try to help them we
just came back we have a project to help
the European refugees so we just gave
talks in Serbia uh we're working in
Kosovo uh we we had a programs in
Greece and uh Romania uh Bulgaria and
we're helping the refugees there so the
idea is that in Buddhism that uh a
person who's a good practitioner should
get into difficult situations
and go into rough places and kind of
semi dangerous places and and help
people there so uh that's the idea of
Kamala Sheila means to act like a Lotus
because
lotuses like to grow in dirty places uh
my Monastery in India you get there by
I'm flying to India tomorrow you get
there by uh Landing in Bangalore you
know right the air the only airport
nearby it's about 8 hours from the
monastery by car and uh I know B is
about 5 million people something like
that uh all the sewage from Bangalore is
raw and it flows out of the city into
this wonderful
Lake uh a a lake of raw sewage and uh
you have to drive right across the shore
of the lake to get to the monastery and
uh it's a long pleasant experience and
uh the first time I saw a lot of lotuses
was there and you know I said stop the
car and there were all these lotuses
growing out of the poooo you know and I
said oh I got to get one of those I got
out of the car and the driver grabbed me
and he said get in the car you know he
said ask one of those kids you'll give
them a rupee to go get it you a Lotus
you know and uh so Lotus is like to grow
in the dirtiest places uh they grow very
well in pooo and mud so in Buddhism we
say that if you're a good person you
should seek out uh difficult people to
deal with difficult situations dangerous
situations uh situations with a lot of
poverty and then you should focus your
efforts on those people so kamila also
implies uh acting like a Lotus okay
growing like a lotus in the difficult
places
okay uh so I'm just going to go straight
through the diamond color
Sutra and we'll stop every once in a
while and do a meditation based on on
kamila's
commentary so uh the very first thing he
does is discuss why is The Diamond
Cutter Sut called Diamond Cutter because
why is it
strange they call it Diamond
Cutter
chy oh they don't mention a diamond in
the whole Sutra okay there's nothing to
do with diamonds in the whole Sutra so
the first thing is kamalashila has to
say you know why is this called a
diamond KRA all right those of you who
who took courses at the three jewels
over the last 20 years probably
forgot uh course six but in the course
uh you know the true meaning of the name
Diamond Cutter it means that uh Ultimate
Reality which is another name for
emptiness King is more powerful than
even the most powerful thing in in in
the physical world so you know I was in
the diamond business uh because of the
diamond uh because of an experience I
had with diam with the diamond but
diamond is the
closest uh metaphor in the world for
Ultimate Reality for emptiness so it's
not emptiness it's a positive thing
Emptiness is an absence of something but
the closest object in this reality to
Ultimate Reality is a diamond okay so
but but that
metaphor we were talking this morning
the Taiwan group uh wanted me to give
them a name for their group they they
sent me some suggestions diamond shine
Diamond
wisdom diamond mountain then I said
no you know it should be called
uh def deficient
diamond or you know insufficient diamond
or something like the point is the
diamond is the highest thing in the
physical reality which is close to
Ultimate Reality and it's not close at
all okay it's not close at all it's the
highest thing but it's not it's not the
ultimate thing okay but it's the best
metaphor you have in this world if you
have seen emptiness directly you might
want to spend your life touching or
being around d
okay uh just to remember what happened
to you okay only for that only for that
reason okay
so kamalashila gives another explanation
of the word Diamond In The Diamond
Cutter Citra and I really like it and I
think you'll like it also he says the
shape of of a very common crystal shape
uh so you know what a diamond's shaped
like right if you played cards before
poker you know there's this diamond
shape you know Queen of Diamonds right
and then the classical shape of a
diamond crystal is
octahedron uh so it's eight-sided
beautiful shaped like that and very
commonly they will grow into a twin
octahedron do you have a picture of that
yeah so this is two Diamond crystals
that kind of got married to each other
you know 100 million years ago under the
Earth and this is called a twin diamond
crystal and it's a very common shape uh
for a diamond and in fact this
particular shape because the grains of
the diamond grow across each other this
this cannot be cut by anything uh no no
substance in the universe can cut a twin
Diamond it's you just throw them away in
the diamond business you sell them to an
oil well company they use them in the
drills in the tip of the drills okay so
Kam Sheila says something
cool he says the shape of it the reason
they call the cutter Diamond Cutter suit
to The Diamond Cutter is that the shape
follows the evolution of a person's
spiritual life okay so in Buddhism we
say that every every spiritual person's
life follows a certain standard
Evolution five different stages in the
life of every spiritual person it
doesn't matter what religion you belong
to what faith you are you will have five
shared experiences as you pass pass
through your life as you pass through
your spiritual Evolution and they follow
the shape of the diamond for kamalashila
they follow this shape
okay uh let's talk about it he says
first it goes to a very the broadest
part of the diamond if you go left to
right represents the first of the five
stages of spiritual
Evolution uh to put it bluntly in
English it's called Uh disaster in your
life okay like people get religious when
there's a disaster in their life you
know they don't care about religion then
the doctor says you have incurable
cancer or something like that I I
remember uh CS Lewis I think he said uh
the day after World War II ended like
the the churches in England were filled
every day during the war and then the
day after the war ended they were empty
again you know so uh people get
religious when bad things happen to them
and when you have a difficult period in
your life life then you turn to
spiritual spiritual life because it's
the only thing that can help you in the
end it's only your spiritual life that
can help you so in Buddhism we say you
have spent countless lifetimes to the
left of this diamond and then the
longest part of your life from top to
bottom the the most number of years are
the years that you spend in sort of a
dull what do you call
it just what do you call it when
somebody's on a drug like you're just
like spaced out trying to make money
trying to build you know gather
possessions and then something happens
to wake you up okay so that's that's the
most years spent is in that kind of dull
stuper uh of materialism or or like that
and then suddenly you wake up because
you get cancer or your mother dies in
your arms in my case three of the six
members of my family died quickly my my
father my brother and and my mother all
died within about a year and then you
get spiritual
okay then uh there's a second stage
around here a sort of a median stage
that we say is is if you're lucky you
will meet a person who will explain to
you why things happen where things come
from why did the stuff that happen to
your life happen to you you know uh why
why did you meet the people you met in
your life who made New York City where
does all these things come from okay if
you're lucky you'll find someone during
the initial part of your spiritual Quest
you will run into somebody who will
explain to you where stuff comes from
like death or New York or or your
husband or your ex-husband okay okay and
uh to save you time I'm going to confirm
you in the second level in the next 5
minutes okay you ready I cannot give a
talk without talking about this okay uh
if you hear this talk once in your life
you reach level two okay I save you
millions of years okay no I'm serious
and it took me 25 years to learn it okay
but I can teach it in about 3 minutes
okay so seriously uh if you hear this
once in your
life uh you're on level two in Buddhism
if you reach a good level two after you
die you cannot go to a bad place it's
not possible okay it's uh it's called a
sensation okay when you reach a certain
level of understanding of pen which I'm
about to tell to you after you die it's
not possible to to be born as an animal
or something like that okay you you will
be born as at least as a human okay so
it's a good deal it's worth the ticket
price of
today's admission okay and by the way
I'm very sorry you ran out of seats we
had no idea how many people would like
to come and next time we'll get a bigger
place
okay uh we just did it at the last
minute and I'm sorry for that and I'd
like to thank uh Nancy and Miriam
and
Chom and can you guys stand up where are
you can you just stand up for a second
no they're probably outside working and
uh Michael we we'd like to thank you for
arranging it on such short
[Music]
not okay so a quick uh a quick pen okay
emptiness
King
uh in the in the ancient Buddhist system
you at the teacher ask questions you
answer if you answer too slow you get
hit especially front row he
all right uh you thought a rosary was
for counting prayers okay uh I'll ask
questions just answer don't think too
much okay answer just honestly and and
and quickly okay what's this
thing yeah good uh if a dog walked down
this aisle came up the steps and I went
like this and what would the dog do with
this thing yeah a young dog will chew it
okay does the young dog see this has a
pen
no so can we say that the dog sees this
as something to chew on and the human
sees it as a pen which one is
correct yeah you can say both are
correct animal rights okay now you can't
say uh the humans are always saying
don't chew on my pen but if the dog
could talk he'd say don't write with my
chew toy you know like you're wasting a
good chw toy what's wrong with you you
know so it's it's sequel next question
is more deep okay if I put this object
here on the chair and all the humans go
out of the room and the room is empty
and all the dogs leave the room and then
the last person goes out and closes the
door then at that time is this object
now a pen or a chew toy which
one you can say neither okay at that
time it's neither that's the true
meaning of emptiness okay and it's no
more uh Mr than done okay I'm sorry to
destroy so many
preconceptions uh okay that's all that's
all emptiness means okay there are
people who teach that it's close your
eyes and see everything is black it's
incorrect it's grossly incorrect okay
why it doesn't help you it can't benefit
you to sit there and close your eyes and
try to see the back of your eyelids say
black it doesn't do anything for you
there are some people who say oh just
watch the thoughts go through through
your mind and let them fade as like
clouds in the sky and this is emptiness
and that's that's also not emptiness
okay it has nothing to do with emptiness
it it doesn't do anything for you if you
practiced that for a long time there's a
classic teaching on that in Buddhism
it's called Chiang it's a special
meditation kamila particularly didn't
like this meditation it's where you try
to just watch the thoughts in your mind
float away and if you do that for you
know 5 years years or something you
become like an absent-minded Professor
okay that's the result of that
meditation you're like you
know where I put my car CU you know you
just get kind of forgetful like it's not
an emptiness okay there's a
very there's a very kind of evil kind of
emptiness which says nothing's good
nothing's bad everything's an illusion
okay that's also very wrong okay it's
nice to help other people peace in the
world is a good thing uh suff is a Bad
Thing war is a bad thing it's not true
that everything's an illusion and some
things are nothing's good and nothing's
bad that doesn't help you okay they
don't make these religious paintings
with uh you know air pollution and dead
people and tonas right they make them
with beautiful gardens and angels and
there are good things and there are bad
there are bad bad things okay so
emptiness just means when all the people
left the room then this thing is
nothing yet okay when we say yet it
means if a person walks up enters the
room leans over here and looks at it at
that moment what does it
become yeah it becomes a
pentan that pen which became a
pen now's the big thing okay pay
attention you can sleep
later is that pen which becomes a pen
when I walk in the room is that that pen
coming from the pen or is that pen
somehow coming from me yeah somehow it's
coming from me can I if it's coming for
me can I close my eyes and wish that it
was a $100
bill it didn't work okay yeah things are
coming from you but you cannot just make
them what you want whenever you want
okay they depend on some other energy
which
means what you did last week okay what
you did last week okay
how do I see a pen when I reach here and
I look at that object on the chair okay
why do I see a pen according to
Buddhism a seed grows in your mind a
seed opens up in your mind out of that
seed comes
a a luminous image of a pen about this
big okay that's called that seed called
in
Sanskrit Karma okay so the seed opens I
I reached here the seat didn't open yet
then I took another step and the seat
opened in my mind a small picture of a
pen comes out of my mind that appears in
the front of my mind as though it were a
pen on the chair okay so that's how
objects that's where your husband came
from uh that's where your job came from
that's where your body comes from okay
they're all flowing out of seeds in your
mind who put the seed in your mind
you did okay uh
when
before okay so if you want no it's like
any other seat if you want to see a $100
bill this week you have to plant it last
week
okay oh Scott ran away because he knew I
was G to ask him for
$100 we're not okay you have
$100 I'm GNA show you how to plant
$1,000 okay I know you're all spiritual
and you don't care about
[Music]
money and I respect
that but just for purposes of
demonstration okay I'm going to show you
how to plant a Karma okay how to plant a
seed all
right uh so if I want to make
$1,000 according to Buddhism according
to kamalashila this is how you make ,000
okay and if you don't want $1,000 that's
okay we spent $5 million
paying the refugees for 29 years to type
in their ancient books we spent $5
million okay and they're free
online we finished all the books in
Buddhism from ancient India it took that
took 25 years 4,600 Texs are finished
they're free online okay you couldn't do
that if you don't have $5 million okay
so money can be
useful uh it's not necessarily a bad
thing okay so here we go I want to make
$1,000 will you help me he say yes he's
so
C you cannot plant a seed without
another person it's not possible you
cannot plant a Karma without another
person the the process of planting a
Karma requires another person okay so
I'm happy because I found someone to
take my
$100 okay it makes me happy okay so a
Buddhist is different from other people
Buddhists if you go to borrow money from
a Buddhist they get a thrill up their
spine
you know
and if you don't then you don't
understand anything okay so he's willing
to take my $100 I'm going to plant a
seed give me your hand left hand is good
luck okay put it up
high then this is how you plant a Chic
seed okay you put it in his hand okay he
closes his hand then then I open my hand
okay when I open my hand who sees my
hand
open yeah I see and he sees he's happy
I'm also happy he made a 100 I'm going
to make a
thousand we're both happy that's the
essence of karma by the way it makes
both parties happy any kind of
transaction in the future of an
enlightened World should be win-win by
definition okay so he's going to make
$100 then when I open my hand that image
comes into my eyes and it brushes my
mind okay it brushes my mind and if I
have a loving intention if I say God
bless you I hope you use it you know
what do you call
Ma I hope you use it happily you know
and then with that intention of love it
makes an impression in my on my mind
okay and within a few hours that
impression becomes a sin Inside the Mind
okay got it then next week something
will happen $1,000 will come to me by
hook or crook it doesn't matter reality
will have to adjust to me
the world will have to adjust to me cuz
I have a seed for $1,000 okay
understand okay keep
it okay okay understand
so that's the meaning of of emptiness
okay emptiness means when the pen was on
the chair before anyone came in it it
wasn't anything yet okay when I got
here a seed opened in my mind because I
did what last
week I shared a pen with someone who I
don't know they're signing an important
contract with ASD publishing in MVA you
know then I gave them a pen okay then
that planted 10 pens in my mind okay
understand that's the real meaning of
emptiness uh
vadra Diamond
sorry so that's here if you get that
explanation in this lifetime you have
reached level two in your spiritual life
okay
congratulations okay I'm not kidding
okay uh it's a very important stage in
your life okay very few people reach in
here is the direct perception of
emptiness during a state of meditation
okay on a
retreat or during your daily meditations
you see emptiness directly okay and and
you can that's very short this is the
narrowest part of the diamond because it
only takes 20 minutes okay it takes
about 20
minutes if you see that directly your
body starts to change into light like an
angel okay and I don't care if you don't
believe
me if you've seen it you don't
care okay I I really don't care but it
happens okay your body starts to change
and and that process is what do you call
it
it cannot be stopped it's a what do you
call it
Unstoppable the
changes irreversible the change is from
this point on the change is irreversible
okay you you cannot change it if you say
I don't want to be Angel it's too
late uh if you have this experience
during deep meditation okay then uh for
the rest of your life you use that
knowledge and you start to act
differently for example travel with
money okay you start to be like uh
different from other people you take
great joy in sharing what you have
because you know it's only going to make
things better he he made $100 I made a,
everyone's more happy okay like your
behavior patterns change and you become
totally loving and totally unselfish
okay because you know it's best for
everybody it's going to get him what he
wants and it's going to give me what I
want so this stage here
is the rest of this life
finally the change in your body is
finished and mind and then you go back
to countless years of being an
enlightened being that's the five stages
in the spiritual evolution of every
person and Kamala Shila says that's why
it's called The Diamond Cutter that's
why the diamond is in this book now I'll
show you something interesting wake up
Mr leha
okay understand so the shape of this
ritual instrument called of vadra in in
Tibetan Buddhism and Indian Buddhism uh
comes from that diamond twin Diamond
okay and these are
the this is when you have your your
disaster the doctor says you have cancer
or that your mother died
okay this is when someone teaches you
the pen you just got there okay this is
the 20 minutes that you see it directly
communion with God you can call it this
is when you're using that for the rest
of your life automatically you become a
better person because you're just
sharing all the time you're just giving
all the time okay and then the widest
part here is you become a an enlightened
being on countless worlds okay we finish
the first of the 25
meditations okay sorry
in China they said could you just go all
night and we
tried we went till like three 4 a.m. I
think but then we all got too tired okay
now we're going to do a meditation
because you can't let go of your cell
phone ever I have developed a meditation
in which you hold a cell
phone
okay
uh and uh can you put that out app up
Scot there's an app by uh Insight it's
called inside
timer this is it okay during the break
I'd like you to go get it don't do it
now cuz your cell phone's
off uh I'll do it for us and it's a
great little timer okay it's a great
meditation timer it makes religious
sounds uh it's not working right
now come on
yeah and what I found in my own life I I
would like to meditate more I and I
found a way to trick
my okay and it's that you set the timer
it's almost at the minimum it's five
minute meditation okay so nobody in this
room can say you don't have five minutes
to do a meditation okay you know that if
you're going to say that to yourself I
can't help you
okay myself either you know I have the
same problem I'm very busy I don't have
time to meditate get the app set it for
5 minutes okay and you'll find you'll
have a revolution in your in your
meditation life okay really okay just
get it it's free okay sometimes I think
they should charge a lot of money so
people will respect it but uh it's a
free app okay and we're going to do a
meditation now five minutes when you
hear the Bell go off you're supposed to
get religious okay
uh and everyone gets quiet and we'll
meditate for five minutes what I'd like
you to meditate on is this shape you
have that
vdra the shape of the
diamond and the five stages of a
spiritual life right number
one disaster disaster number two the pen
okay number three in deep meditation you
see emptiness directly number four you
use it for the rest of your life to have
a beautiful life okay and then number
five you just become a Buddha okay so
I'd like you to we're going to do a
meditation on the shape of a diamond the
five stages of life and I'd like you to
try to pinpoint where you are okay where
are you in those five stages okay I'll
give you a clue since most people are
probably in two by now two has two parts
okay the first part the easier part
is that oh pens are coming from me or
money is coming from me or how my
husband acts is coming from me okay
because of how I treated people last
week all right that's
easy but seeds in your mind also create
the thoughts you hear in your mind okay
you are not the Thinker you are a
listener you are the
witness of of thought seeds opening in
your mind okay which means you can't
meditate
you don't have any control over what
your mind thinks about okay your mind
will throw up to your
mind images from how you treated people
last
week okay if you made people sad last
week and since karma is always enhanced
by the time it opens you will be
depressed this week okay and you can't
do anything about it okay that that's
why we're doing the study in the mental
hospital it's very interesting okay you
can't my teacher you knew Ken R right
people would come R I feel depressed you
know they said I need an appointment
with they go upstairs you know I was
some I would translate his English into
English and
uh and then they say I'm depressed
remember say he'd say he'd say oh okay
and they say what should I do in p and
he
go be
happy and and then they they like and
I'm waiting they'd say okay you can go
down now i' say R you know depression is
not like that you can't just tell
somebody be happy what are you talking
about he said it's too late to to not be
depressed okay you planted those seeds
last week when you made other people sad
so when they open you're going to hear
depressed thoughts in your mind you
can't stop it it's too late push a tree
back into the ground it's too late you
know if if you don't want to be
depressed next week I can tell you how
to do it but you're going to be
depressed the rest of the week I'm
sorry okay when you understand that the
thoughts in your mind are also ripening
from the seeds you planted last week
you're at the advanced stage of level
two that's the one that keeps you being
born as an
animal okay so it's important to
remember okay here we go we're going to
close our eyes for five minutes
try to think
about where you might be on on the five
paths where are you you know how far did
you get did you have your big disaster
in life yet or should you pray for
one okay here we go how far along are
you you have to know because you're
going to die you have to you have to
finish before you die it's a race okay
here we
go
for
for for
h
[Music]
that's not the
Bell
for for
all
okay take three deep breaths three deep
breaths before you open your eyes three
deep
breaths okay good you can open your eyes
I'm going to skip some of the minut I'm
going to do two things number one I'm
going to skip some
meditations and number two I'm not going
to give you a
break so you were supposed to have a
break but we started late okay and uh
they're going to kick us out at a
certain time and I'm sorry for
that uh but that's the custom when you
have a decent place to teach
so uh if is that all right we just go
straight through
okay there's a beautiful meditation
based on why the Buddha is sitting in a
garden when he gives this teaching okay
and uh I'm going to skip that one okay
uh we just don't have time I got to get
to the meat of things uh then there's a
a very beautiful meditation about how
the Buddha
leaves the garden to go ask for food uh
for his food and and why Buddha only
eats so little every day and and why he
asks other people for food and that's a
beautiful meditation and if you want to
learn those uh there's a website do you
have it can you put up the knowledge
base there's a website that has 5,000
hours 5,000 teachings on it 25 years of
teaching uh and it's all free okay
and you can go check uh check for the
kamila and uh you can uh it's in several
languages but but you can just type in
kamila and and if you're interested uh
you can learn these other meditations
okay from the the knowledge base okay
it's a website and it's free okay uh the
next thing that happens in the Sutra is
that Lord Buddha goes into
meditation and I'm not going to teach
you that one we'll skip cuz we did it
this morning with some we'll skip that
one then the next one is that the monks
arrive 2 and a half thousand monks
arrive in uh the garden for uh teaching
I I went to that Garden I was teaching
uh in Baya I was teaching The Diamond
Cutter under the Buddha tree under the
Bodhi Tree which was pretty awesome in
for the first time it's ever been taught
in English and uh we had a cool time and
and uh and then that was the Millennium
the next day so I I drove like 14 hours
to shristy cuz some people said the
world was going to end because computers
couldn't do z00 and all the nuclear
weapons would go off and uh so I thought
if I'm going to die I'd like to be
sitting where the Buddha taught The
Diamond Cutter so I went there and I sat
there at midnight and nothing
happened uh but uh 2 and half thousand
monks coming to the Garden to to request
the teaching of Lord Buddha they all
touch their head to the feet of Lord
Buddha they circle around Lord Buddha
three times and then one of them whose
name in Sanskrit is
sabuti uh stands up and he says may I
ask a question uh before he asked the to
ask the question there's a custom in in
in monk monk ethics when you request a
teaching you drop your Shaw from your
left shoulder so he dropped
his Shaw from his left shoulder then you
have to kneel on your right
knee uh and then you have to hold your
hands like this in Buddhism you have to
put the thumbs inside and then you
request the teaching so he he he
requests the teaching he says I have a
question and and and would Lord Buddha
answer my question Lord Buddha says yes
go ahead and he says I my question has
three parts all right and subi says if
you're a bodh Safa if you are someone
who is pledged to save the whole world
then how should you live and how should
you practice and how should you think he
asked these three questions okay if you
are a pledge to to help the whole world
then he asked us how should you live and
how should you practice and how should
you think and for the rest of the Sutra
Lord Buddha answers that question okay
in
brief he says uh the way you should live
is that you should live in a state of
hope uh to serve the world and to make
the whole world a better place okay you
should how you should live is in a state
of vision or a dream to serve the whole
world that's how a body saer should
live uh secondly sorry how should you
practice you have to understand where
the pen is coming from okay you have to
understand where things are coming from
okay and that's it that's Buddhist
practice okay just understand where
things are coming from then you can fix
the world okay if you understand the pen
is coming from whether you gave him a
pen or not or you you know you want a
partner then go help a lonely person
plant a seed for a lonely part I had a
famous lady in Europe she's like number
one Oprah Winfrey of Europe and she she
came to my talk and she she asked can I
talk to you afterwards I said yeah okay
she says I'm very famous I said I know
and she said uh and everybody knows
everything about my personal life and I
said yeah and she said and I don't have
a
boyfriend and everybody knows and it
really bothers me you know it's like is
there a way to plan a seat for a
boyfriend so like I taught her this
boyfriend planning seed you know you got
to be careful with it because if you do
it too much you get three
boyfriends uh that's another thing that
happened to another person uh
but she did everything properly there's
four
steps if reality is coming from my
mind then there are four steps to
planning a scene any kind of scene okay
so if I want to be financially I don't
want to be wealthy okay I don't have any
much things I don't I'm smart enough to
know if you have a house with 12 rooms
you have to clean 12 rooms okay so I
have a tiny house it has the tiny rooms
and it's comfortable it's good for
meditation I tried to live in a cave it
doesn't
work okay they have
spiders uh poison snakes and wolves
visiting me and I said I'm going to get
a little house you know so I don't want
to be you know Warren Buffett I just
want to have a quiet little house that I
don't have any debt there's no mortgage
I'm financially independent that I don't
want to think about money I want to be
free from money I don't want to be
controlled by money I don't want to have
to think about my credit card debts and
I don't need to be rich but I want to
not think about money I want to have
that much
money and and you can plant it okay so
we just did it with him okay there are
four steps she s in
abidos fourth chapter
okay starts like that okay four steps to
planting a Karma number one you should
be
writing if you want anything if you
don't want anything in your life you
don't have to write okay number one
decide what you want okay like I would
like to have I would like to be free of
money I would like to not think about
money okay number one uh number
two find another person who has the same
goal okay find another person who who
who shares a similar goal you know I
would like to be financially independent
okay I'd like to do what I want go where
I want buy what I want and not think
about the credit card bill at all
somebody else pays it somebody else
takes care of it okay I asked Scott this
morning I sent him an email I said I
said I need some money from
India and and he and he said well why
are you writing me I said I don't know
how to take money out of the bank yeah I
I haven't done it for like I don't know
many years you know somebody else takes
care of it I don't know
okay that would be better right and then
uh third
step help them to get what they want
once a week for one hour period That's
all help them to get what they want once
a week for one hour it's called Jor do
it Nike what's it called just do it yeah
people just do it okay one hour a week
if you don't want to be financially
independent don't do it if you don't
want to have a beautiful relationship
don't do it if you don't want to have
ballet Health at 60 something then don't
do it okay you can do anything okay you
can change your body I used to have a a
handicap I couldn't walk sometimes and I
changed it I just changed it okay four
steps it's not like some miracle if the
world is coming from your mind you just
just fix
stuff okay got it you're supposed to say
what's step four
G step four is uh very cool uh a a
normally planted Karma under normal
conditions may take thousands of years
to
open okay and uh if you want to wait
thousands of years don't listen to step
four okay step four is called tanuk and
it means uh if you have a certain
attitude about the seed you
planted because Prana rides on the
thoughts because they are tied together
because where you put your mind prto
will also go if you focus on the
kindnesses you have done to other people
that ripens the seed faster my Shanghai
students call it they gave me a new name
I don't know the Chinese okay they say
Oh you mean mama chicken sitting on the
egg I said yeah that's pretty good okay
it means if you want to feed the karma
up you have to set aside a certain
period of the day my llama said before
you go to bed as you you know stretch
out I don't know about you when I get
down on my bed this thing happens from
my mouth I can't stop it even if I want
to it's
like I'm so happy like the bed is the
best thing in my life you know and I
just like ah it's like involuntary noise
comes out of my mouth you know and the
uh and when you get to the that point
between then and the time you sleep
think about the good seeds you have
planted okay think about the kindnesses
you have done to other people if you're
on a specific program to become
financially independent then tonight
when I when I go
ah then what's the next
thought yeah I gave the money to that
dude whose name I don't even know what
is your name what's your name me m
m oh I gave me some money today that was
so
smart you know and it was kind kind and
smart like that's a Buddhist perfect
Buddhism kind and smart you know and you
know it's just going to bring me
beautiful things and it already brought
him beautiful things and it's a win-win
and you know when you are when you take
pleasure in your own Good Deeds
uh that's Buddhism that's the essence of
Buddhism okay like of course you've done
a lot of mistakes in your life we all
have okay but when you focus on them you
just you just make them stronger okay so
focus on the things you've done nice for
other people there's no expiration date
a kic seed will stay in your mind
indefinitely kic seeds are more powerful
than the body if the body happens to die
by accident before the caric seed opens
that seed will find another body okay
all right the seed cannot be destroyed
all right so focus on it make it grow
faster those are the four steps okay
don't say I didn't tell you if I see you
next next year you're complaining about
your credit card don't blame
[Music]
me and I'm not kidding the the lady in
uh Europe whose country I can't
mention
uh she did it she actually did what I
asked her to do which makes her like one
out of a million
and uh she went to the nursing home she
served and she number one I want a
boyfriend number two find a lonely
person number three go to the nursing
home take care of an adopt an elderly
lady who has no family right visit her
once a week for 1 hour and then when you
get home just be happy about the nice
thing you did okay like that you can be
happy about two things number one I did
a nice thing number two I'm trying a new
system other than nightclub and online
dating you know like I'm trying a
different system I'm planting the boy
I'm not looking for the boy okay got the
difference planting is a lot more
predictable all right you can uh plant
the different qualities you want also
but I don't have time to teach you that
come to a DCI event okay uh so she did
it she actually did it then she said she
was walking down what's it called voska
Vos yeah if you know Europe you know
which street she was walking down VOS
street she ran into a guy physically she
was she was looking at a dress in the
window and she smashed into this guy
this big handsome you
know they got married she missed my
talks last year I was kind of
irritated just cuz you got the boy you
don't come to see me she said no gisha
I'm sorry I was having a baby you know I
was giving a baby I said okay that's
okay you know and she's very happy okay
you can do stuff like like that I was in
Shanghai the guy said I I have to uh no
that's a baby this the guy who's
complaining he he he grabbed me after
the talk he said you told us last year
if we did the stupid for steps we could
have anything we want I told you I
wanted something I didn't get it then
I'm like I'm sorry did you do the four
steps yes did you do number one yes I
wanted I I decided what I wanted was to
make $10 million did you do step number
two
yes I found another person who wanted to
make you know like a similar amount of
money did you do step number three yes I
actually went and helped him one hour a
week did you do step number four he
looks down I was in the diamond business
when you're dealing with somebody and
they look down they're about to tell you
a
[Music]
lie and he goes like then he says yeah I
did never before I said how many days a
week well you know pretty much how many
days a week I'm like I don't know
sometimes I did it once a week I said I
told you I had to do it every evening
you know that's why you didn't get what
you wanted he says I didn't say I didn't
get what I wanted I said you just told
me you didn't get what you wanted he
said I didn't get all of what I
wanted I said what what happened he says
I only made 8
million you know I said then you know
what I want to say to Scott is you know
we should try to do what we talk about
um
but what I but when you're a teacher you
have to be tough to the people you know
said that's why you lost $2
million you know you have to do step
number
four okay so anyway you can use it okay
if reality is coming from you then you
can adjust reality of course when the
money comes to you you have to do
what you have to reinvest it you have to
give it to some charity you pick your
own charity okay make your own charity
call it the you know the roach fund or
whatever you want you can name it after
your mom or your dog or something okay
my dog used to be George I have a George
fund and you make your own charity and
you give it keep giving and then it just
keeps cycling okay help other people
find boyfriends take your husband to the
nursing home don't stop going to the
nursing home okay and you'll never get
divorced all right it's
cool okay so
to bring it back to Diamond CRA the
Buddhist says how should you live you
should dream of a perfect world where
everyone is just planting the things
they want and everyone gets everything
they dream of okay number one number two
how should you practice think about the
pen over and over and over okay anytime
you want something in your life anytime
you have a challenge in your life pull
out a pen that's that's why I use a pen
nowadays I'm using a cell phone a lot
because the kids don't use pens
anymore
uh okay the pen is coming from you the
cell phone's coming from you okay so
just remember that's how you should
practice says Lord Buddha and then the
answer to this what was the third
question how should I think Lord Buddha
for the rest of my life how should I
think he says how should you think don't
forget number
two okay don't forget number two
especially Under Pressure okay
especially Under Pressure okay by the
way that's where the conversation goes
to if you're a real bodh SAA you should
be taking other people to Nirvana this
is your job that's a job description of
a body SAA you should be leading this is
Lord Buddha speaking in The Diamond
Cutter sura you should lead every person
to Nirvana but then he says something
weird okay then he says but when they
get there nobody gets
there okay when you finally push someone
into Nirvana nobody reaches Nirvana
nobody goes to Nirvana okay then the
Buddha like takes a takes a break and
everyone's like huh you know what do you
mean there's nobody there I'm going to
teach you okay uh here we
go and this is how to think okay this is
the answer to the third question Okay
the third question is how should we
think and Lord Buddha says don't forget
what I told you about the pen even when
things get hard especially when things
get hard pull out the knowledge you have
so
you're you went to work you know the new
uh liberated women in the world
especially in China before you just had
to cook and raise the kids now you have
to make the money and cook and raise the
kids and the husband is watching videos
okay and uh so you're dagging home and
you're really tired you know and you're
you you you you took the kids to the
school in the morning and you you worked
all day then you know it's a sacred duty
of a woman in China to buy the
vegetables on the way home and you have
to spend like 45 minutes picking out the
best bites I and then you you know and
then you come home and you're hoping for
a hug from your husband you know and you
open the door and you say honey I'm here
and the husband says you're so
stupid okay did it happen to you I don't
know and you say why and he says dinner
is late I know I had to take the kids I
had to F the grocery maybe you could
have helped me you're so stupid
okay then what's the natural reaction to
that yeah you respond with the same
thing you I'm not stupid you're stupid
you're stupid if you think I'm stupid
because I had to go to the grocery store
and you know I've been working all day
maybe you could have just picked up some
vegetables on the way home or maybe you
could have worked today you know and uh
so the the the natural reaction is to
say the same thing back to your husband
okay
now when you say when you call someone
stupid who hears
you who hears you when you give the
money who sees your hand open you see
that plants the karma when you call
somebody's stupid who hears it you hear
it it plants a seed in your head that
when you open the door and the caric
seed opens somebody
says you're stupid okay how did you
plant that
seed last week you asked the kids I got
mommy has to go to work early on
Wednesday please be ready with your
shoes on at 8:00 to go to school a
little bit early okay and they say yes
Mommy
and then you come in at 7:45 and they're
jumping on the bed and they don't have
their school clothes on and the the
shoes you don't nobody knows where the
shoes are you know and you say you
are you're the stupidest kids in the
world you know something like that okay
who hears
you you here and the kids here okay when
you hear those words yourself it brushes
against your mind the anger glues it the
anger fixes it and then it makes an
impression on your mind and that becomes
a karmic seed okay then you come home a
week
later through no fault of your own right
you are not to
blame right and your husband goes off
and starts calling you stupid okay are
you to blame or not you're always to
blame you're always to blame okay got it
in Buddhism there's no such as thing is
it's not my fault or for no reason at
all okay it's always your fault you come
in the seat opens just like with the pen
okay the seat opens and the husband says
you're stupid okay now here's the
Crux what's the stupid how can you prove
you're stupid at that
moment respond yeah respond to him call
him stupid all right then you can prove
that he is
correct okay why cuz when you plant the
new seed then you go next week you have
to go week early tell the kids they're
going to do something stupid cuz they're
also coming from you then you'll get mad
at them and you'll plant a new seed and
then you what's that cycle called the
two
names
sansara there are many Saras by the way
there are stupid husband stupid calling
Saras they just keep repeating over and
over okay then there's big ones called
life okay The Wheel of Life s okay why
am I talking about this we're supposed
to be answering the question why when
you guide people to Nirvana does nobody
reach nirvana okay what does that mean
okay to answer that question you have to
understand the husband when you walk in
the door and he calls you stupid okay at
that
moment there's two husbands in the room
you got to understand that y do me do
there's a husband who's and there's a
husband who's missing okay got it
there's two husbands in the room there's
a husband who's there and there's a
husband who's missing all right there's
always two husbands in the
room okay who's the one who's
there the one who came from yelling at
the kids last week okay that one is
there that husband is there he's the one
who called you stupid who's the husband
who's not there nice nice uh slide Scott
who's the husband who's not there not my
fault for no reason at
all okay got it understood that husband
is there or
not the one who's not your phone is he
there I just told you it's always your
fault now let's say it again if it's
always your fault and there's a husband
there who's not your fault does he exist
or not yeah he's not there never was
there couldn't be there isn't there
never will be there cannot be be there
impossible okay but you now now here's
the husband who's your fault because you
yelled at the kids last week and you
planted a caric scene here's the husband
who is not your fault who
doesn't even exist okay
listen which one do you get angry
[Music]
at which one do you call
stupid yeah the one over here it doesn't
even exist okay every time you ever had
a negative emotion in your whole life
you were angry over something that
didn't
exist that's emptiness King okay the
second husband who's not your fault he's
not there he never was there but that's
the one you're angry at and that's the
one you create yelling kids
with got it it's like a
tragedy okay no all sadness all pain all
suffering in the world is created by by
Phantoms being angry at someone who's
not even there okay all war all hunger
all poverty created by someone who's not
even there that's the big I don't know
irony of life
okay how can that help you reach Nana
what's the definition ofana can somebody
give me a definition ofana if you want
to impress people you can do it in
[Music]
tibetan which means ending your negative
emotions permanently
because you understand the husband who's
not there you understand it and and
according to Buddhism that's the only
way to destroy your anger forever okay
why open the door husband
says you're
stupid and then you're like
you're yeah okay
then you run past the husband to the
bathroom you're stupid and you're
looking in the mirror right you're so
stupid okay that's okay that stupid
person is
[Music]
there okay
understand so according to Buddhism the
only way to reach nirvana and the only
way to stop your anger and your jealousy
and your desire uh is to realize
that the people you're angry at or that
you desire the things you
desire don't exist they never existed
okay understand yes look I understand
what you're
saying but those guys at the airport had
two huge boxes at Dunkin Donuts and I
was really debating whether to go with
or suggestion to have a green smoothie
or just walk over and say can I have
three of
those
yesterday are you telling me the Dunkin
Donuts not there yes I am saying that I
saw it gu they opened the box there was
chocolate there was Maple there was a
sprinkled one that I was really thinking
about what do you mean it's not
there it wasn't there okay the donut
that you think you can get by taking
one is not there okay the donut that you
can get by sharing
one is always there okay got it
understand you cannot have a desire if
you understand where things are coming
from okay you can't want to take
something from someone else if you
understand where it's coming from
because the only way to get a donut is
to share
Donuts got it same with money so now I
taught you the most important three
things in life money partner and
donuts okay it's all the same okay so
you can't not reach nirvana
unless you understand King emptiness
it's not possible okay you cannot reach
nirvana when you reach nirvana you
better understand that the person who
reached nirvana wasn't there then some
people misunderstood that right they
said cuz Buddha said your mind and body
disappear your mind and body disappear
you reach nirvana and your mind and body
disappear what did he
mean the mind and body which you cannot
mold into whatever you want disappearing
okay the mind and body which are going
to die the mind and body which are going
to be sad depressed unhappy you destroy
them you cannot be sad anymore and
frankly your body cannot grow older if
you really
share then then Buddha said when you
reach nirvana you lose those two you
lose that body and you lose that mind
okay it doesn't mean you disappear okay
you get to keep the body that you
planted and you get to keep the mind
that you planted okay clear all right it
doesn't mean you pop you know you
disappear and you don't have to pay your
taxes this year
and it's not like that okay the old body
disappears all right and the old mind
disappears okay that's Nana so when you
reach
Nana uh nobody reach the old person is
gone okay now let's start the teaching
I I want to get to this part okay
so Buddha gets kind of wrathful with the
booty which is common for a teacher my
teacher used to get rled with me like
every five minutes for 25
years and uh it's a good it it it molds
you it builds
character so
uh so buddy asked the Lord Buddha a
question look I I you know it sounds
mystical and everything
uh by the way put that on your lap it's
good luck it's it's not good luck to
have your foot on it okay good
uh so buddy says the Lord Buddha you
know it sounds cool that nobody's there
nobody reaches Nirvana the husband I was
angry at was never there you know that
sounds really cool there's no self
anatman right there's no self I like it
it sounds very
mystical you know but it's a little hard
to buy lord Buddha you know it doesn't
make sense for three reasons so we're
going to get we're going to go there
okay cuz we only have like 20 minutes
left it's a little hard to buy lord
Buddha when you say there's no Michael
okay when you say emptiness means
there's no Michael okay it's just hard
to buy and Lord Buddha says why and
Saudi says three reasons number one by
the way Lord Buddha gets wrathful he
says so Buddha if you think there is a a
Mel uh you're no Boda I don't I cannot
call you a bodh SAA you're not a bodh
SAA okay if you think there is a person
who achieves
Nirvana then you're not a buod ster you
can't call yourself a buod ster so sabui
gets a little
irritated he doesn't call Lord Buddha
stupid because he knows about
that but he says
um three problems Lord Brother number
one first problem is so somebody used to
not understand the pen there was a
Michael last year who didn't understand
the pen and then he went to this talk at
Lincoln Center okay we don't have don't
tell people G Michael talked in the
smallest Auditorium in the back okay
just say he was at Lincoln Center
teaching and
um uh
then then so there's this person I I
didn't know who was called me all my
pain and who was making the kids bad and
then you talked about the pen and then I
understood the the bad kid and then
irritating husband were coming from me
okay every irritating person you ever
met in your life was coming from you
they are direct mirror of your own
behavior okay I understood that Lord
Buda but when I understood it and I
stopped responding to my husband and
that kicked me into
Nirvana then was the person who didn't
understand it okay in the past who used
to yell at the husband and the person
who's now in Nirvana who realizes it
shouldn't yell at a husband are those
two people connected or
not are they linked or not did one come
from the other or not was there a a a
tie between the two were they somehow
connected or not because if there's no
Michael you cannot say they're connected
okay then if that's true random people
should pop into Nirvana any old time and
some people should get stuck outside of
Nirvana forever okay if there's no
connection between the person who was
yelling at the husband and the person
who went to the teaching and then later
stopped yelling at the husband if
there's no connection between Michael in
December and Michael in
March then then how can you say anybody
got free is that what you're talking
about how can there be any how can
anybody get to Nirvana if there's nobody
okay that's his that's the first problem
learn Buddha second okay ready are you
okay you got awful
[Music]
quiet Lord Buddha you know did the
husband yell because the lady uh because
I yelled at my kids last week yes so is
there a connection between the person
who does the karma and the person who
gets the result of the karma are they
connected or not Lord Buddha has to
say yes of course
otherwise you could do anything you
could hurt people and get good results
okay there has to be a connection
between the person who did it and the
person who got the nice result or the
bad result okay that connection is
called
Michael the thing that runs from
Wednesday morning kids yelling to you
know next Tuesday evening husband
screaming the person between those two
the person that connects those two
events is my
you can't say Lord Buddha that nobody
reaches Nirvana you can't say there's no
Michael what are you talking about you
want another one okay one more he's from
China not really uh third
one uh when you let's say you didn't see
your mother for I don't know five years
or something okay let's say you're
really busy you couldn't get back to
mvar or something you didn't see your
mother for 5 years Okay so when you when
you go to the airport to pick up your
mother in Miami or something okay then
now you're standing there and you're
looking you you're trying to pick your
mother out of a crowd and then suddenly
you do right oh that's my
mom how do you
know how do you know that's your
mom you have to say I recognize her I
remember her I I recognize her face
she's she's 5 years older but it's still
pretty similar you know that's my mom
so are you connected to the person who
met her 5 years ago yes there must be a
connection otherwise you would take
everyone in the airport
home you know and make them dinner I
don't know which one of use my mom but
uh just covering my bases here you know
okay all right there must be a
connection between the person who who
knew your mother before who saw her face
before and then five years later the
person who picks her out of a crowd in
the airport is there a connection or not
yes there must be okay there must be and
that connection is Michael Michael over
time so Lord Buddha when you say there's
no person when you say nobody reaches
nirada I don't know what the heck you're
talking about it's just crazy you know
anatman you know there's no Swami G you
know it's crazy I don't understand what
you're talking about okay what's the
answer to this conundrum anybody want to
take a shot
what's Buddha mean when he says there's
no person there connected to the husband
who's
yelling there was no not existed at
all when when Buddha said nobody reaches
Nana or there's no Anton what does he
mean does he mean there there's no
connection between doing something nice
and getting a nice result 5 years later
or seeing your mother and recognizing
her 5 years later or having been an
angry person and now being a completely
calm person because you're not mad at
nobody
anymore is there connection between
those people yes yeah of course there's
a connection between those
people okay I'll give you another
clue here's the connection between the
guy who yelled at the kids and the guy
who got the got yelled at by his wife
okay here's the connection between the
two is it it coming this way or is it
coming this
way now you can answer
what yeah it's coming from me it's
coming from me when Lord Buddhist says
there's no Michael what does he
mean there's no Michael coming this way
okay there's no Michael who's not coming
from how you treat other
people cool there's no Michael who's not
coming from how you treat other people
and that's emptiness that's coning
that's the point of the diamond cutor C
okay it's the big deal about the diamond
color
Citra a Michael who is not flowing out
of the seeds planted by how he behaved
last week towards people
doesn't exist okay never existed okay
there's no Michael who does karma and
who experiences the results later that
Michael doesn't exist if you think he
just comes from anywhere okay he's also
the connection is also coming from you
what happens if you lose that
connection what happens if you don't
have season in your mind to have that
connection it's called Alzheimer's or or
Autism okay you can't connect the
present to what happened five minutes
ago you keep asking the I take care of a
90-year-old lady guess
why uh I took her to I spent 500 bucks
on her uh two nights ago I took her to
the Four Seasons uh restaurant in
scotdale oh my God it really pushed my
credit card over the limit um but
uh you know she can't she keep asking
you the same questions you know she's
saying what did you do yesterday it's
good to see you Mike you know she forgot
your name Nick I finally won this battle
he and I were competing for her
attention and uh she said who is that
nice boy who came uh he's been helping
here for like 5 years and uh who's that
nice boy who came the other
day and uh she doesn't have the seats to
connect the present to what happened 5
minutes ago okay so for
her uh the lady of five minutes ago
doesn't exist you understand okay it's
coming from your own mind your
connection to what happened in the past
is coming from your own mind last
thing
uh kamila's called it the Cocoon the
Cocoon okay he calls it the Cocoon I
think there's a picture in your in your
reading
somewhere there's a butterfly what
number is
that number eight 16 16 oh wow you guys
really went a long way 16 is a is a
butterfly he says
uh the Michael who yelled at the
children jumping on the bed was the
caterpillar the Michael who came home
and got yelled at by his wife life is
the
butterfly and the Cocoon in which the
that the caterpillar crawled into 7 days
ago before he came out of the Cocoon
last night and got yelled
at someone created the Cocoon that
cocoon is called Anton or elizabeta or
you know you create the Cocoon you
create the thing called
you okay the Cocoon is also created by
you the Cocoon is seven days long
okay and your life is like that that's
you okay that's you so we're going to do
the last meditation all
right and and and go on the knowledge
base and watch this thing okay go on the
knowledge base and get the whole
meditations I can't do 25 in 2 hours I'm
sorry and you'll also fall
asleep I've experienced
that
okay all right let's do a
meditation one last meditation okay
choose a person in your life with whom
you are having some challenge right now
in your life maybe it's your boss at
work who doesn't understand you maybe
it's your a
partner uh who doesn't appreciate you uh
maybe it's your
children who don't behave how you would
like them to pick any person in your
life who's a challenge for you right now
and I'll do the same thing
now to fix
them I'm going to stop planting seeds in
my
mind I'm going to stop behaving like
them okay so the person I have in mind I
don't know they're just kind of
irritating and
insensitive they hurt my feelings
sometimes
and so in this during this meditation
for the next five minutes till the the
ding goes
off uh we're going to think about how
possibly I might be planting that
behavior with my own behavior okay so if
I could stop then they would stop okay
that's how to stop irritating people
shooting them is not a clean
solution okay here we go
five minutes on how the most irritating
person in your life may have been
planted and may continue to be planted
by me doing the same thing to other
people okay here we go five
minutes
for
for for
three deep breaths take three deep
breaths
okay open your eyes
good uh so you can see from the
the the text today is The Diamond Cutter
Sutra the essence of the diamond C Sut
is emptiness don't forget that emptiness
means the husband who
is not there when someone's yelling at
you the husband who's not there is the
one who is not
your fault got it that's emptiness does
it help you will it help you if you
remember which you can't until two hours
later first time okay it gets faster and
faster okay yeah Emptiness is supposed
to help you okay if emptiness is if you
understand it correctly it becomes the
biggest help in your life okay
understand if you don't understand it
correctly you're just going to lose your
keys all the time
understand just meditate on your breath
or something okay it's it's not
emptiness okay if you understand what
Emptiness
is then it can help you your whole life
okay things you don't like you can stop
them things you want uh you can get all
of them okay emptiness makes it possible
so we couldn't do many of the
meditations I'm sorry uh what I would do
if I were you the the one or two people
in this room who are ambitious
uh I took a photo of each of the 25
meditations you know just because I like
to meditate with my phone in my hand
where is
that
a yeah I I took pictures of each of the
pictures and I put them in my
phone cuz it's nice to have your phone
in your hand okay so like that's the
butterfly picture okay and and I I get
the butterfly picture
up and then I turn on the meditation app
okay so since everything's on your phone
you feel
comfortable okay it's
real okay okay so I I I bring up the
butterfly picture I'm on a plane you
know I'm busy I'm always on a plane if
I'm not teaching I'm on a plane I got so
many
miles where were we we landed where they
said I'll we'll take you in a car to the
gate China yeah and there like three
people from the airline waiting at the
gate they said we'll take at the end of
the ramp they said step down the stairs
to the runway and we'll take you to the
next gate you know I said why they said
you're like zillion miles you know
you're a valued customer I said well how
far away is the gate it's the next gate
over I said I think I can walk it you
know
so you know I'm busy but on the plane or
waiting for the plane the plane is late
I'm so happy when the plane is late I
pull up my butterfly picture I turn on
the app the phone is where it's supposed
to be in my hot little
hand and I'm meditating you know at the
gate and uh it's powerful it's super
cool okay get the free up inside
timer take photos of the things in the
book okay and then see if you can
remember what it means okay some of them
I didn't teach you there's your mom that
you're going to recognize okay because
you built a cocoon
called you okay there's the the postman
who's the
postman that's the guy who delivers
letters that you wrote to
yourself okay don't blame your husband
for for delivering to you the letter
which you wrote to yourself when you
yell at the kids last we got it don't
blame the
postman you're going to open the letter
letter it's going to say you're
stupid okay who wrote it who wrote it
you did last week okay don't yell your
husband he's just a postman
okay and then there's the guy in jail
okay who's that is there a connection
between the person who used to yell her
husband and then now the new intelligent
person who knows that that's just going
to make a worse husband
okay cuz the husband's coming from me so
goes through all those meditations
there's there's the lady yelling at her
husband okay you you I gave you most of
them without you knowing it okay and uh
there's the pen coming out of your mind
okay got it and do five minutes
each uh for a couple weeks and your mind
will totally change okay you will be in
a different place okay you'll be happy
you'll be really really happy okay